<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>ТехнологоблогЪ</title>
		<link>https://www.kvdm.dev</link>
		<description>Observe existence, drink tea, cognize.</description>
		<pubDate>22 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<item>
			<title>Telegram Bot as a command interface for Docker Daemon </title>
			<link>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/telegram-bot-as-a-command-interface-for-docker-daemon/</link>
			<description>The cause enforced me to start searching for an alternative communication channel to ssh for managing my home server is a tunnel agent that is wrapped up in a container. The agent is responsible for keeping a network tunnel established, but from time...</description>
			<pubDate>23 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/telegram-bot-as-a-command-interface-for-docker-daemon/</guid>
		</item>
				<item>
			<title>Data convertion with Redframes and Dataset </title>
			<link>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/data-convertion-with-redframes-and-dataset/</link>
			<description>During active development, table schemas change frequently to correspond to up to date application requirements. Relational DBs are not that well at it as a lot of operations have to be made, you know it as migrations. Schemas not change only, but...</description>
			<pubDate>23 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/data-convertion-with-redframes-and-dataset/</guid>
		</item>
				<item>
			<title>Colorize printed text to get eyes focused. Termcolor </title>
			<link>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/colorize-printed-text-to-get-eyes-focused-termcolor/</link>
			<description>Working with  extended file attributes, i have to do many necessary operations. Updating attributes goes through a search by scanning their values, filtering them and then setting new values up.</description>
			<pubDate>15 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/colorize-printed-text-to-get-eyes-focused-termcolor/</guid>
		</item>
				<item>
			<title>Derivative table of basic functions. Matplotlib. Visualization </title>
			<link>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/derivative-table-of-basic-functions-matplotlib-visualization/</link>
			<description>During reading math essentials i lacked of imagination about how a derivative of different basic functions looks like. Matplotlib and some python code helped me out. This is my visual cheat sheet table.</description>
			<pubDate>2 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/derivative-table-of-basic-functions-matplotlib-visualization/</guid>
		</item>
				<item>
			<title>Getting selected elements by a time series range. Bokeh </title>
			<link>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/getting-selected-elements-by-a-time-series-range-bokeh/</link>
			<description>As a newcomer to Bokeh, i would like to know what the events have to be handled to figure out the selected elements on a  timeseris plot by a range tool to process them further on a server side and what an object receives those events, Plot or RangeTool.</description>
			<pubDate>10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/getting-selected-elements-by-a-time-series-range-bokeh/</guid>
		</item>
				<item>
			<title>Sourcegraph is heavyweight </title>
			<link>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/sourcegraph-is-heavyweight/</link>
			<description>As i don't remember how and where i used technologies in my experience i wondered what profit  Sourcegraph could bring me at searching the code repositories and for potential use in a company. To test it out i chose a  stand-alone server option to run...</description>
			<pubDate>30 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/sourcegraph-is-heavyweight/</guid>
		</item>
				<item>
			<title>Storing related accounts data in the TOML files. Visualization. NetworkX graph </title>
			<link>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/storing-related-accounts-data-in-the-toml-files-visualization-networkx-graph/</link>
			<description>Until this point, i stored accounts and their secret data in .ini, .csv, .txt, .pem files and etc., for example credentials, access keys, certificates. Many simple things can be described by and stored in those file types, but accounts have been...</description>
			<pubDate>5 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/storing-related-accounts-data-in-the-toml-files-visualization-networkx-graph/</guid>
		</item>
				<item>
			<title>File System based file changes history on snapshots. LVM. ZFS. BTRFS </title>
			<link>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/file-system-based-file-changes-history-on-snapshots-lvm-zfs-btrfs/</link>
			<description>After stopping usage a cloud disk and transferring data to my own devices i step forward and would like to find a solution of storing text file changes history, other files formats aren't considering as they aren't editing by me.</description>
			<pubDate>25 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/file-system-based-file-changes-history-on-snapshots-lvm-zfs-btrfs/</guid>
		</item>
				<item>
			<title>Drop a cloud disk in favor of storing data on the phone and laptop. FreeFileSync. KDiff3 </title>
			<link>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/drop-a-cloud-disk-in-favor-of-storing-data-on-the-phone-and-laptop-freefilesync-kdiff3/</link>
			<description>Idea to exploit the laptop and phone storages instead of the Google Drive payed plan came up into my mind as i have much free space on them along with not much data in the cloud around 110Gb when laptop total space is 512Gb, phone 256Gb. Also,...</description>
			<pubDate>20 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/drop-a-cloud-disk-in-favor-of-storing-data-on-the-phone-and-laptop-freefilesync-kdiff3/</guid>
		</item>
				<item>
			<title>Simply patch what is unextendable. </title>
			<link>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/simply-patch-what-is-unextendable/</link>
			<description>An issue, that i can't extend a method __str__, was encountered when i retrieved a list of objects from a third-party service and printed them to see the details, but i got uninformative output. Due to that, i dove into source code to figure out what...</description>
			<pubDate>24 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/simply-patch-what-is-unextendable/</guid>
		</item>
				<item>
			<title>Beneficial Chrome replacement. Vivaldi </title>
			<link>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/beneficial-chrome-replacement-vivaldi/</link>
			<description>I had been using Chrome for a quite long time as many others certainly. That's a good, modern, powerful browser. During usage of it for a job purpose, i found more and more features it's good to have to simplify different operations and keep them...</description>
			<pubDate>23 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/beneficial-chrome-replacement-vivaldi/</guid>
		</item>
				<item>
			<title>Laptop bootloading time extreme growth. SystemD </title>
			<link>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/laptop-bootloading-time-extreme-growth-systemd/</link>
			<description>If you have Linux installed on your laptop you may once encounter OS is bootloading abnormally slow what is happened in my case and it has taken around 44 seconds where 26 seconds in the userspace level. I've noticed after pressing the power button on...</description>
			<pubDate>9 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/laptop-bootloading-time-extreme-growth-systemd/</guid>
		</item>
				<item>
			<title>Columnar DB performance in action. DuckDB </title>
			<link>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/columnar-db-performance-in-action-duckdb/</link>
			<description>This article is intended to represent only one simple thing is a fundamental difference between columnar family and standard row-based databases by an example. Roughly speaking, you may need a column-based database if working with a complex...</description>
			<pubDate>14 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/columnar-db-performance-in-action-duckdb/</guid>
		</item>
				<item>
			<title>Fix ERR_CERT_AUTHORITY_INVALID error python clients get while proxying. Mitmproxy </title>
			<link>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/fix-err-cert-authority-invalid-error-python-clients-get-while-proxying-mitmproxy/</link>
			<description>You may find out as me that after proper setting Mitmproxy up python https requests end up with ERR_CERT_AUTHORITY_INVALID error while other http clients are working with no problems. Quite unexpectable, isn't it?</description>
			<pubDate>10 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/fix-err-cert-authority-invalid-error-python-clients-get-while-proxying-mitmproxy/</guid>
		</item>
				<item>
			<title>Рассмотрение абстракций, их взаимосвязей и сложности библиотек встраиваемых БД </title>
			<link>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/rassmotrenie-abstraktsii-ikh-vzaimosviazei-i-slozhnosti-bibliotek-vstraivaemykh-bd/</link>
			<description>Часто возникает желание иметь простейшую архитектуру сервиса или программы, в которой будут отсутствовать избыточные компоненты и межсетевое взаимодействие. Это ощутимо сокращает силы и время на их реализацию, поддержку и погружение. Чтобы...</description>
			<pubDate>24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://www.kvdm.dev/articles/rassmotrenie-abstraktsii-ikh-vzaimosviazei-i-slozhnosti-bibliotek-vstraivaemykh-bd/</guid>
		</item>
				</channel>
	</rss>